<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact copy of some passionate letters and verses as they were writ and sent by a person of quality to the Lady --.</title>
            <author>C. D.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35723</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D11</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13326023</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13326023</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35723)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1548:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact copy of some passionate letters and verses as they were writ and sent by a person of quality to the Lady --.</title>
                  <author>C. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 91, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for N.R. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Epistle dedicatory signed C.D.</note>
                  <note>Errata sheet bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99072:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True and Exact COPY Of ſome Paſſionate LETTERS AND VERSES, As they were Writ, and ſent by a Perſon of Quality to the LADY -</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>N. R.</hi> in <hi>St. Pauls Church-yard.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99072:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99072:2"/>
            <head>TO Sir CHARLES GAUDY Knight and Baronet, OF DEBUHAM In the County of SUFFOLK.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe Papers lighting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Hands, and finding ſomething in them, no leſs remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able than different to the general
<pb facs="tcp:99072:3"/>Practiſes of the preſent Age; I could not force my ſelf to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of their Concealment, and indeed the greater was my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to their Publication. When, Sir, you were brought by the peruſal of them freſh to my Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as being owner of all thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualifications they ſo live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repreſent, and are requiſite in Perſons to whom things of this nature are Dedicated; Theſe Reaſons I ſoon found too power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be refuſed by what I could alledge againſt giving you this trouble, and skreening this my Friend under your Protection. The greateſt fault you'll find in him, was, that he Lov'd; but he Lov'd well, which perſwades me, that according to the Character you deſervedly bear in the World,
<pb facs="tcp:99072:3"/>you will find ſomething that ſo nearly reſembles your ſelf, as will make it difficult to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the one from the other. He like you has felt that Paſſion ever produced in a Soul frait with Love and Tenderneſs, which makes me preſume you'll be pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to eſteem this no improper Addreſs; and really, Sir, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe Perfections, with the addition of ſincere Friendſhip and Generoſity, which I never knew him failing in. I ſhould yet deſpair of his Pardon, for making his Letters publick; had I not preſented them to your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage, it having been his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Care and Concernment theſe many years to keep them from the cenſorious World, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Retirement, little di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb facs="tcp:99072:4"/>from being Buried to all his Acquaintance, except when his Quality rendred his publick Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance unavoidable; and ſo fond was he of his own Choice, that he would often proteſt to me, he found more Content in his little Cell, by Contemplating upon that dear Perſon to whom theſe Letters were writ, and her <hi>Idea</hi> that was always preſent with him, than Courts or Crowns could give him; In ſhort, nothing was able to draw him from his Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which would bear many things to be ſaid in his Commendation; but I ſhall forbear all flouriſhes, either upon his Faith or Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in this place; being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, you'll find in the following Papers, what will convince you of this, better than any thing I
<pb facs="tcp:99072:4"/>can poſſibly ſay; and withal, how great a Reproach his Conſtancy is, to the Levity of all Pretenders to Love in our days; which makes me have very little more to add, only that <hi>Methridatia, Delia</hi> and <hi>Aſteria,</hi> all imply one and the ſame Perſon; and accordingly my Friend aſſum'd the three ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Names, <hi>Callimichus, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierchus,</hi> and <hi>Orantes,</hi> in order to carry on their Amour with the greater Secreſie. If Sir, you take any ſatisfaction in looking upon the excellent Endowments of his Mind, tho' far ſhort of the great Perfections of your own: I hope you'll be pleaſed to pardon my Preſumption in Dedicating this little Book to you, whoſe Protection for it is the greateſt of my Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and whoſe Mercy I will not
<pb facs="tcp:99072:5"/>deſpair, of having had a thouſand occaſions of knowing your Genero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, which extends it ſelf to all People, and more particularly to,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR, </salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humble, and Obedient Servant, <hi>C. D.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99072:5"/>
            <head>Some paſſionate Letters and Verſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInce this, Madam, Addreſſes it ſelf to you, ſhrowded under ſuch a permiſſion as can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, from the violence of thoſe apprehenſions that attended my laſt; You may eaſily gueſs how I wiſh every Letter laden with ſuch a legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Gratitude, and adorn'd with ſo ſubmiſſive a Reverence, as might a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeably repreſent the power of your Merit, and the paſſionate Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I have of it. But Madam, it is as equally above my Hope, as my Capacity. And I ſhall only beſeech your Ladyſhip, you will illuſtrate the Senſe of the one, by your Knowledge of the other, and then, tho' you may ſtill believe I want enough to make
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99072:6"/>the return proportionable, yet you will no longer doubt my paying all. Theſe are not, Madam, the ſuddain Impreſſes upon Senſe only, nor the immediate effects of that Fury which ſo commonly ſurprizeth, tho' I muſt confeſs I have with Impatience and Delight felt the influences of <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia</hi>'s Eyes; but all that conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, years, and a hopeleſs reſiſtance could do, have ſo fataly convinced my reaſon, as what was but at firſt my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, hath long ago ſo much be come my Judgment, as pardon me for having often concluded with my ſelf, 'twas no crime to acknowledge or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to what I ſaw was inevitable. Yet Madam, they who have ſet the moſt refined Rules, and made ſuch Diſcoveries the nicities of Romances, have never doom'd them to ſo long a confinement, nor produced more mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes for an expiation; if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſilent Oratory of Unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the dumb Eloquence of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for ſo long a time paſt, can be any obligation to your being farther acquainted with what had ſo blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99072:6"/>a beginning, let me be forgiven: for ſeeing you would admit its conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance, and I here proteſt by all that's Sacred, it ſhall never know the violation of your Commands; and can a Paſſion deſtitute of pretences, by the merit its paid to, deſtructive of its own being by Arrogance or Diſobedience, and hopeleſs of any Favour but what its Humility may intitle it to, be rejected or deſpiſed by one whoſe Generoſity is extenſive enough to oblige the World, and yet diſcerning enough to know the propereſt Objects for that venture; put me paſt this doubt, I beſeech you, and let me know, that till you have a greater exception to my admiring you, then that I do admire you, it ſhall be allowed: Oh Madam, charm me with a favourable Return, as you have done with your Beauty, your Humour and your Wit, and perm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t me to tell you, that all the Reaſon and Senſes I have, are tributary to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of your Perfections; nay, ſo ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revocably fixed, that like the Eart<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, it cannot looſe its Natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99072:7"/>may its prolifick Virtue, when it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth benighted under the abſence of the Sun, or where it never knows the power of a fertile Shower; Forgive this, and let me know it, unleſs you wiſh me the unhappieſt of Men.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Madam,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <l>'Twas Heat and Light that firſt made Mortals pay</l>
                  <l>Devotion to the beauteous Orbe: and they</l>
                  <l>Whom Balmy Sweets, and perfum'd Flowers made gueſs</l>
                  <l>Their Gods ſuch fragrant Manſions did poſſeſs.</l>
                  <l>Pay but what Love and humbleſt Zeal inſpire,</l>
                  <l>Sweets became Incenſe, and Sacred was the Fire.</l>
                  <l>'Tis true, then Zeal, not Merit, made Men bow,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch blind Honours you may diſallow</l>
                  <l>But you've diſperſed the Cloud and Merit here.</l>
                  <l>Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ines the Power and the Worſhipper</l>
                  <l>Forgive me then, if I implore you now,</l>
                  <l>To lay but at your Feet an humble Vow.</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99072:7"/>
                  <l>The Paſſion which I pay ſhall ne'r diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence</l>
                  <l>With Duty, Promiſes, or Reverence,</l>
                  <l>At other Altars I'le ne'r kindle Fire</l>
                  <l>Beyond what you'll allow, I'll not aſpire</l>
                  <l>When theſe don't guide my Paſſion, let me Die,</l>
                  <l>Scorn'd and unpitied in my Infamie.</l>
                  <l>Till then, deign but to ſee thoſe radiant Eyes,</l>
                  <l>Inform me of my Fate, for there it lies.</l>
                  <l>Oh let that ſweet and gentle influence,</l>
                  <l>Which charms at once our Reaſon and our Senſe,</l>
                  <l>Drop Joys int my Soul, from whence ſhall riſe.</l>
                  <l>All that makes a grateful Sacrifice;</l>
                  <l>And think not, Madam, that you are leſs</l>
                  <l>Your own, for being thus the Happineſs</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>—Polierchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>WHat ſweet <hi>Mithridatia</hi> terms Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, ſhe has no reaſon to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatisfied withal; ſince being confined by no other obligation than her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>role, nor no longer by that, than
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99072:8"/>whilſt ſhe is treated with all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and ſubmiſſion that can be due to a Princeſs; it may more properly be called Generoſity, the Deſert as well as Demerit of what ought to be paid her, having long ago juſtified a Remove; 'tis therefore generous <hi>Mithridatia</hi> that makes her obliging <hi>Mithridatia.</hi> And ſince I can find out no other reaſon to hope for her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, than that which makes her give it; She can be no longer tyed, than ſhe declines making uſe of her Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and happy <hi>Call.</hi> That it ſo falls out, for had <hi>Call,</hi> by ſurprize, or her own negligence diveſted her of it, ſhe could not have failed of regaining it by the acceſſion of new Force, or by the weakneſs of that, by which I muſt have maintained it; but having laid down ſome part of her own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, having deſcended from her Throne to raiſe a Peaſant to the foot of it; it would be a greater violation of her Generoſity to depreſs him now, than if ſhe had never exalted him; You ſee Madam, the Terms I own to ſtand upon, I think it tacitly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:99072:8"/>all the Duty of my Soul, for my Happineſs, and that being ſo cloſely allied, I muſt chuſe to be miſerable when I ceaſe to be obedient; if you will therefore take a right eſtimate of the diſproportion between poor <hi>Call.</hi> and charming <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> there can be no room for diffidence, but what ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſevere <hi>Mithridatia</hi> the other day ſaid of her ſelf, or from an Opinion I ſhall conſpire to be the executioner of my own Delights, preferring Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and Affliction, before Honour and Content; I think I may lawfully Swear, I ſhall not do this, and as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure I am againſt the other; Pardon me, charming <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> that I vow, amongſt other things, to have admired you for being juſt contrary to the Characters you gave of your ſelf, and I am ſure I am not miſtaken, the Conditions upon which you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my Reſpects, juſtifying my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; if therefore the having all that one can wiſh, or think of to Love and Admire, be any ſecurity that one ſhould Love and Admire it. If our Reaſon and our Senſes can conduct
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99072:9"/>us to the ſole Object of our Deſires; I am undoubtedly brought within proſpect of all that Intereſt, Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Reaſon can think moſt va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable; there is no Soul ſo ſtupid, whoſe Delights are not comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe, not to be fixed when theſe are attained, is to make it the pittifulleſt piece of the Creation; but we are better informed by thoſe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior Agents which all acquieſce in their Centers; And is Man alone the worſe for being endued with the Happineſs of a nobler, and more certain guide, than all the World beſides, to be falſe to this Direction is to turn Beaſt, to deſtroy the Delights we aſpire at, and wilfully extinguiſh that Glorious Light which the bounty of Fate hath allowed us; there is therefore fine <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> a period to a rational Man's Inconſtancy, a time when he is paſt another Choice, by the Laws of his own Content; If you can there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore allow me Reaſon enough to know what I like, you muſt conclude me paſt a farther ſearch; and that tho' I am as far from its poſſeſſion, as if I
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99072:9"/>had not found it, yet that I know where all that is delightful duely, I thought my ſelf ſecure for one halfe Hour, but I am called and can only ſay, that I am with all the Paſſion and Reſpect imaginable <hi>Mithridatia</hi>'s Admirer: altho' I am infinitely ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, Deareſt <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſtricteſt inquiry, I cannot inform my ſelf, whether has the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt prevalency upon my Soul, my Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or my Reſpect; yet I cannot but confeſs the different Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they infuſe, are oftentimes my di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance, the preſent conteſt about this humble Offering, hath admitted of ſuch a Diſpute, as ſhould I ſtay to hear what both could ſay, I might probably loſe the opportunity, you will ſee the ſucceſſion of this, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carried in favour of my Deſires, I am reſolved to hope it will be as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable that I have waved the Rules of Ceremony, by ſo ſuddainly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing you with this trouble, as that I ſhould have paid you that Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the omiſſion of this: Sweet Charming <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> tho' I am not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99072:10"/>ſo far raiſed upon the ſteps to Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, as to believe my Paſſion were the gratefulleſt Sacrifice I can make you; yet I ſhould be too low for one that is admitted to make uſe of his Ambition in the ſervice of ſo fine a Woman; if I thought you took no notice of its neglect, I will not ſo much as doubt then your forgiving this, but looking upon the greateſt Indulgence to be moſt properly a Virtue of the greateſt power, I beg of you to uſe it as a thing of your own Creation, the Genuine effect of that Beauty, Wit, and Generoſity which hath made me the moſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, and the moſt faithful of Men. Oh <hi>Mithridatia!</hi> How do you allay the pleaſure I take in this Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, by ſaying it cannot be, and if it were it could not make you hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py: Had you only mentioned your doubt, I had not deſpair'd of its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, but if its aſſurance cannot confirm your Happineſs, How little do I fear you wiſh it; 'tis true, I ought not to ſet ſo narrow limits to what deſerves the whole World. But
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:99072:10"/>Madam, ſince not a Multitude but Fidelity; not Extent, but Obedience makes both Dominion and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Why may not you enjoy both? where the Territory is not ſmall, as the Duty is large; It is not here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined by thoſe common Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Convenience or Satisfaction; Let but <hi>Mithridatia</hi> propoſe, and if I obey not implicitely, let her make me as much the Object of her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, as I wiſh to be of her Favour: Why ſhould you be ſo great a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the happineſs of being Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in the Breaſt of your Admirer; it muſt be the deſerts of the place you are admired in, that prevent it, and thoſe methinks you have too long known to turn ſo ſeverely upon now: beſides, I reſolve to transform them into ſomething ſo fit for the ſervice I deſign you, that you ſhall not only make me a better Lover, but a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Man than ever I was; this claim to your kindneſs you ought not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it being the conſequent of ſuch a Merit, and ſuch a Love, as I beg of you to aske Sweet—Whether it
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99072:11"/>were not a crime to part them,? If you will let her be the Prieſt, ſhe ſhall at our next meeting, pronounce them inſeparable, and then ſhould my jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney prove my death; I ſhall have all the ſatisfactions, that being parted from you can admit; and if there be ſuch a thing in the next State, as retaining our leaſt ſentiments here, they will have Purity and Innocence enough to be my Companions there, Adieu.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sweet as the Breezes Eaſtern Winds con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey,</l>
                  <l>As breath of Cows, or Roſe at break of Day.</l>
                  <l>She breaths a Wit, as ſweet as Flowers to Senſe,</l>
                  <l>And o'er my Soul ſhe hath ſuch influence,</l>
                  <l>That when but near me in a Thought ſhe's come,</l>
                  <l>My Breaſt for nothing elſe can find a room.</l>
                  <l>Did you know fine <hi>Aſteria,</hi> you would ſay,</l>
                  <l>She's gently Great, Obliging, Sweet and Gay.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99072:11"/>
                  <l>Converſe finds there its firſt and chief Delight.</l>
                  <l>The Splendor of the Day, and Pleaſure of the Night.</l>
                  <l>'Twas there I left my Soul, and found her Mind,</l>
                  <l>The Wonder, yet the Pleaſure of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind:</l>
                  <l>Farwel all Joys, except ſhe will allow,</l>
                  <l>I come to beg, and fetch them from her Brow.</l>
                  <l>Ah! there I'de kneel, and pray I might expreſs,</l>
                  <l>The Beauties and the cauſe of Happineſs,</l>
                  <l>But ſhe well knows they're to her ſelf confin'd</l>
                  <l>There bounteous Nature, all her ſtrength combin'd</l>
                  <l>To make the fineſt Body, nobleſt Mind.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>SInce all the content of my Life de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon giving you theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iterated aſſurances of my Paſſion, you muſt, fineſt <hi>Mithridatia</hi> forgive me, if I ſeize upon all opportunities to tell you, I am now arriv'd to that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99072:12"/>degree, that living and loving you, is one and the ſame thing, and that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the expiration of the one, can be the deſtruction of the other; the loſs of your Favour will make me miſerable in exceſs, but the end of my paſſion depends upon nothing but death, too violent a remedy for any thing but the dreadful misfortune of your unkindneſs, not ſo gaſtly, if I know my Heart, as to make me rather bear that burthen than ſhun it; but if you will incourage me to throw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way theſe melancholy Reflections, and make me deſire to preſerve my life for your ſervice, Accept of that Love which properly makes a Life, and which, under the ſevereſt diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhall be pleaſant to me with your kindneſs, the greateſt Bleſſing I beg of this ſide Heaven, and of Heaven I beg it. Since the Reverence and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, I will uſe ſo great a Bleſſing with, ſhall be ſuch as Angels ſhall not think Criminal, my deſires have been regulated by that Virtue which makes my Paſſion ſuch: My Friendſhip ſhall be Juſt and Conſtant, my Fidelity
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99072:12"/>ſhall be as uncorrupted, as the ſweet <hi>Mithridatia</hi> I adore; and the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration I have for you ſhall be ſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, as excluding all poſſibility of other Temptations; My Love ſhall Saint us; confirm this Paſſion of no common Nature, by all the Holy Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations that ſuch things can admit: Let our Vows, our Promiſes make as firm a Contract as Love can tye, and if I purſue you not all the days of my life with ſuch unceſſant peals of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as to Mankind, is now a ſtranger, make me the unhappieſt of Men; for I am content you have this Reſerve of baniſhing and ruining me, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I digreſs from what I ſay, you need not tell me of what any Mortal would dread, but I never preſume to trouble you with that. Did your confidence in me bear an equal ſway, I ſcarce know what could hinder you from preferring my Love before that of other Men, nay, all the World, ſince nothing in it ever lov'd a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man more, or more ſubmiſſively; the uncertainty of telling you this, and the care I muſt always take to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:99072:13"/>the niceties of your Reputation before my own Happineſs; make me decline the Bleſſing of being near you, to give you theſe more diſtant Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, I ſhall not expect you ſhould be under ſo great inconveniencies in this place to make me returns of the ſame nature, but I muſt, and do up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my knees beſeech you to make your Eyes and Tongue the meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of my Happineſs, you ſhall, with your permiſſion, receive, when I can make an anſwer to them this way, for God above knows I had rather ſpend my time in this, or in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of your converſe, than in all that my ambition or wiſhes can aſpire to, Adieu, forgive me this, <hi>Callimicles.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>IV.</head>
               <p>I Come ſweeteſt <hi>Delia,</hi> upon ſo ſad an Errand, as will require both your Generoſity and Compaſſion, to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the misfortunes that attend it; 'Tis, Madam, to take my leave of you, and by that Word and Action of Part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to tell you I am as unhappy as a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:99072:13"/>Man diveſted of all he can call or think ſatisfaction can be ſuppoſed to be; 'tis true, the great part of my Life looks like a continued parting, but diſtance is a great aggravation of ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and I am more unfortunate, as the ſpace is greater between me, and that which alone can allay the troubles of my Life, or add to its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; The truth of this, Madam, is, as great as that I have a Being, and fixed upon my Soul in ſuch indelible Characters, that to live and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for you above the reſt of the World, is one and the ſame thing. Give me, deareſt Madam, the delight to know you deſire it ſhould be ſo; and it ſhall not be in the power of any thing Humane to make it otherwiſe; This Paſſion implanted by all the ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable Arguments of Reaſon and Inclination, ſhall purſue you and your Intereſt, in all the ſhapes of friendſhip Gratitude and Service, ſhall pay you all thoſe Duties the cenſorious World admits in acquaintance, and all thoſe which Reverence and Fidelity impoſe upon one tyed by Vows and Love; if
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:99072:14"/>this condition charming <hi>Delia</hi> preſents its ſelf agreeably enough to obtain your Opinion of its being a Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs deſirable; ſcruple not to let me know it; 'twill be the only compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I wiſh in my journey, a permiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to entertain my ſelf with an aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance you will inſtate me in ſo great a Bliſs will be all I now deſire. Oh my admired <hi>Delia,</hi> make me as irreſiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly yours by Obligation, as I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitably ſo by Paſſion; not that I can wiſh more reaſons to be ſo, than I have, but that I would not have you want one to conclude me ſo; I hope you will forgive me if I am now more importunate than ordinarily in peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioning your Favour, and that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to give you this Note at this time, 'tis to beg of you, and I do it this moment upon my Knees, that you will add ſomething this After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon to what I know you deſign me, that may convince me of my being in your Favour; let me in plain words without a daſh, receive ſome ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, as you do not uſually part with; in return I will preſent you
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99072:14"/>with Services ſhall be legible enough for you to underſtand, no Mortal was ever more in love, the Sun can as well ceaſe his motion as <hi>Po.</hi> loving, you ſee how little I prize my own preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, when I am always acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you with what you make uſe of to my deſtruction; However, I muſt, and do with all imaginable ſincerity, proteſt my Vows and my Love, are the never to be parted Companions of my Soul, joyn'd by the force of Inclination, and ſecured by Laws, both Humane and Divine. Adieu.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Joy is taking of its flight</l>
                  <l>Deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> How ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Live when Life is out of ſight,</l>
                  <l>I believe I ſhall dye.</l>
                  <l>Nor is the Eye at leiſure here</l>
                  <l>To ſuffer the inſtructions of the Ear</l>
                  <l>The dull inſtructions of Advice</l>
                  <l>May fit the Happy or the Wiſe,</l>
                  <l>What can the wretched have from Hope?</l>
                  <l>Or can it my Deſtruction ſtop?</l>
                  <l>Or if it could, 'twould be a grief,</l>
                  <l>To find in abſence a relief.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99072:15"/>
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>MY Deareſt Dear Lady, every way Dear to poor <hi>Call.</hi> Where alone it is the faithfulleſt Servant li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, ſearches for what is moſt valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon Earth, his Pleaſure, his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and his Love terminates all their Wiſhes there, diſtant from thence every thing looſes both its Nature and its Name: Quiet is a ſtranger, Content is not to be found, Time, the Soul, and Eſſence of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing turns to torment to the then dear Authoreſs of all my Joy I have, and inſeparable from my Thoughts. Doth <hi>Call.</hi> ſend this little and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Atom of his Love, from larger Worlds of Thought; this Seaſon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made him a Creature of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation and Devotion: I do from the truth of the one, and conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the other avow, that I am ſure I know his Soul ſo well, as to ſwear for him; he has more Love, more Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, and more Fidelity for dear <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> than all the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99072:15"/>for the reſt of her Sex; Oh Madam, I am in no humor to Lye, and yeſterday being Sunday, where I eat the food of Angels, may all its Holy nouriſhment turn to my deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, if ever I forſake or love my charming <hi>Mithridatia</hi> leſs; this is not the impreſſion of a ſuddain Paſſion, no Madam, years before you ever knew it was my Adorable and admired <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> my Choice both by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Inclination; But alaſs, What a Bar has Fate thrown betwixt us, will you be angry if I repeat what I told you the laſt time I had the Bleſſing to ſee you, come, it muſt be, it will be ſo; The old Parliament Gentleman chear'd up after Sixteen years deſpair. I ſhall yet live to own to the World a Paſſion, that you too much truſted in your laſt; Ah <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> I am ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle able to ſupport my ſelf under the affliction of your disfavour, or under the ſeeming guilt of any thing dero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory to that reſpect and love, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which I have vowed to live and dye, as I have ſent this to <hi>Mithridatia</hi> to beg, and beg it I do with all the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99072:16"/>earneſtneſs imaginable, that ſhe will ſend me one kind Line by this Bearer, and to diſſipate my Fears ſhe will bid me come and lay my ſelf at her Feet; Firſt to tell her of my Love, and then how it was my Brothers Buſineſs with my Mother, which I have been forc'd to adjuſt, there being accounts between them, that has created me much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but how can I talk of trouble, when<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have all that can be called ſo in your unkindneſs; that I cannot, bear, oh dear Madam, let me no longer be left deſtitute of all I can think or eſteem happineſs, let not that be laid to my Charge, which whenever I contract upon my ſelf, I withal bring a Sorrow that is as inconſiſtent with my Health, as Light and Darkneſs; Well, my dear <hi>Mithridatia,</hi> adieu, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe me not for my Demerit, nor yet for my Age, for upon my Salvation, I have Love enough to hide thoſe blemiſhes, and Courage enough to dye for you, rather than live for any Woman elſe upon Earth; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you of the truth of what I now ſay, I am come this moment out of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:99072:16"/>my little Grove, where I have invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the Holy Angels to witneſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me to my Creator, whenever I prove falſe to my Vows. Ah Madam, I muſt loſe the Image of my Maker, and the reaſonable Soul wherewithal he has endued me, when ſuch villanies enter my Breaſt; and till then diſdain me not from being the moſt paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate, the moſt faithful, and the moſt obedient of Men, <hi>Callimachus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>VI.</head>
               <p>I Should be unfortunate beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, if the Malice or Deſign of prejudiced perſons ſhould leſſen me in the Favour of her, to whom I pay a Homage of ſuch a nature as I think in the Eye of Heaven, cannot be deemed criminal or defective, if there be ſuch a thing as allowance for Humanity, if ſweet <hi>Mi.</hi> find it guilty of either I ſhall ſubmit to her Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but 'tis too unhappy to be at the mercy of others, for what they are not concern'd in. I beg you to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between thoſe who prefer you
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99072:17"/>before all the World by Inclination, and thoſe whoſe envy pay your Merit an unwilling acknowledgment in their emulation; we both in our way do you right, but I wiſh ſuch a Joy as my own Happineſs is not more engaged by it, than the content I take in your being more deſerving than all the World. I beg leave to tell my ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Mi.</hi> there dwells not in the Soul of Man, a Paſſion more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly guarded by Fidelity and Reſpect, as the one will always make me love and admire you, the other will always oblige me to do it in the manner you will approve, ſo that till you find I grow diſobedient, give me not death by your unkindeſs, and when I change from what I have ſo often vow'd to Heaven and you; then my Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Mi.</hi> may I become not only the ſcorn of every one, but an exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puniſhment of him that made me; May I dye unpittied, and my Grave be filled with infamy and reproach, when ever I forſake the only Woman upon Earth I ever lov'd (for by that great Argument Compariſon, it is ſo,)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:99072:17"/>then why will not my Adorable <hi>Mi.</hi> be contented with my Love. When ſhe can tell her ſelf it is ſuch an one as the dull World is yet a ſtranger to; it purſues you Madam in every ſhape, Obedience, Duty and Submiſſion are its attendance; my Fortune and my Life ſhall follow you to the laſt peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od, be but then contented I ſhould live, and that impulſe which has told me, ſo a thouſand times, tells me now we ſhall yet live to get of the bright ſide of the Cloud, and end our days to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and if I fail you, may I never ſee the face of the Holy Beatitude: Adieu; Let me hear the next Poſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you deſign me more miſery than I can bear. <hi>Calli.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>VII.</head>
               <p>I This day, Madam, found two Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers with Superſcriptions that ſoon recalled thoſe Thoughts, that either publick or private Buſineſs had ſet on work, like Atoms that Stormy wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had ſet on float, retire when the Calm arrives; that Centre, Dear <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatia,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99072:18"/>(if I may ſay ſo) did all the wiſhes of my Soul repair to, yet not to be ſo firmly fixed, as to be without ſuch agitations as Love produces, I was glad to ſee, yet feared what I was to ſee, and now <hi>I</hi> find my fears were not ill grounded; for after all the redreſs I found was a long reproach, Two whole Letters loading me with Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Falſity, that never ſound a moments Reſt in any part of my Soul. What? did I go down to you to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void you? And did I call at—going and coming, on purpoſe to miſs you? Had I ſpent my time in ſome of your Buſineſs, that I might keep it from your Knowledge? Why ſuch contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions? Why ſuch impoſſibilities, to contrive my misfortunes with? Why did you not throw a thicker Veil over your unkindneſs? A dim ſighted Man may look through this, but I muſt not ſee, yet you force me too; For why ſuch pleaſure in reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up my Vows? Why ſuch ſuddain Declarations? that you wiſh no other cauſes of my Service, than my Service; you would have ſcorn'd that Notion
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99072:18"/>at another time, as much as I prefer the Honour and the Love of Serving you before any other thing. and ſo you bid me adieu. Ah! How well do you know that is a farewel to all my Content; and how little I deſerve this, let your own Reflections judge? You applaud my Generoſity, Madam, But would it not prove the grateful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt effect of it? To bid adieu to my pretenſions, and make in that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, room for the more fortunate. Ah! Madam, I am ſcarce ſit to write in the Humor I am in, my Soul being heavy to death; The All-ſeeing Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers know, I wiſh the World yours, and my little one in it, you ſhould be ſure of in ſpight all my great misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes; Your intelligence, Madam, I much admire, but were you halfe ſo kind to poor <hi>Call.</hi> as to lying Fame, you had been greater proof againſt ſuch weak Aſſaults. Well, Madam, I'l trouble you no more now, but ſince you have made me ſo frank a Preſent of all my Vows, they come ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to my Relief. I ſend them to you all again, born upon the Wings of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:99072:19"/>thouſands more, and tho' they never reach the breaſt of my unjuſt <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia,</hi> I lay them all at her Feet with Love and Friendſhip. Well, for your Comfort, I am as little happy as you wiſh me, but when I am that falſe wretch you repreſent me, let Diſeaſe and Misfortune be my portion, and when I break one of the Vows I have made, ever to love you, may I be point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at for the baſeſt of Men. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>VIII.</head>
               <p>HAving but one ſource, deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> from whence I derive all my Happineſs, and but one refuge to appeal to in all my misfortunes, I hope you will no more repine than wonder, if you be the object of all my Addreſſes; 'tis from the joint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both theſe, that this preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion arrives you, and the Fate of both depending upon you; it were as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable as impoſſible to expect any other redreſs; Give me leave there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to tell you, that retiring into this little Cell, to ſpend thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:99072:19"/>I can call my own in contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of what is ſo diſtant from all but my Thoughts, I was aſſaulted with ſuch melancholy Reflections, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Diſcourſe of charming <hi>Delia,</hi> which Subject I too well remember, (that my endeavours to love her leſs would be an obligation) if you had obſerved how it ſurprized and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed me; then, when I was with you, and when I had a thouſand plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures (like Showers upon a Flame) to allay it: What influence do you think it hath now, when I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to withſtand the cruelties of that Conſideration. For my part, I am of opinion it gave me more trouble and more misfortune than you wiſh your greateſt Enemy; but there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no Entertainment worſe than that of Sorrow, I will at leaſt exclude it from this Paper, and tell my <hi>Delia,</hi> that having lain under this preſſure till it became inſupportable; I was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to that recourſe of thinking more upon <hi>Delia,</hi> than what ſhe ſaid, which I own to have given me all, and the only quiet Moments I can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99072:20"/>in abſence; Had you ſeen how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently I ſearcht thoſe Treaſures of Bliſs for an Antidote; I cannot but think in pity you would have given one your ſelf to the Man that dies without you, and wiſhes not to live but for you; ſurely you would <hi>Delia,</hi> yes and have reverſed the very mention of what carries with it Death, and ſo great an impoſſibility of Obedience: If I err in this, dear Madam, or am thought to have done too much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue my ſelf from the tyranny of Grief, my ſubmiſſion ſhall yet inform you, I am unacquainted with preſumption; nay, I will rather chuſe to dye and love you ſilently, than loſe one drachm of your eſteem by an unpardonable Arrogance; Ah <hi>Delia</hi> did you know how madly I dote on you, you muſt be troubled at that cruciating thing you ſaid to me; Tell me Dear, tell me who is that happy Man, I muſt be made a Sacrifice to, for were there not that in the cauſe, why, after ſo many years ſervices of Duty and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity (the ſtricteſt Man ever paid) Should I be wiſhed out of the World,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99072:20"/>for there is no difference betwixt that, and what you would have me do; However, uſe me as you pleaſe, for never, never will I change from the vows I have made ever to love you, and to aver the Truth of what I now ſay, could I invent greater Curſes than thoſe I have already wiſhed on my ſelf, when ever I am that perjur'd Villain to renounce my Fidelity and Faith with you, I would by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you, never to perſecute me more with that which will bring me to my Grave; but as my Religion binds me to believe thoſe I have already ſworn to, will diſrobe my Soul of all the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and Bliſs I wiſh it; ſo will they, I hope, be of conſequence great enough for you to depend upon poor <hi>Pol.</hi> who has no life under your disfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, which if you'll deign to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, ſhall be laid at your Feet with more Devotion, and more Delight, than ever Gums or Incenſe were offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the moſt Seraphick Hermite. Adieu, my moſt admired <hi>Delia.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:99072:21"/>
               <head>IX.</head>
               <p>'TIs Joy upon Joy, Dear Madam, to have a long, (probably) an unlucky day, crown'd with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of hearing from ſweet <hi>Aſteria.</hi> Thoſe Evenings are the propitious times that bring me a recompence for all my pains; that Salves all, Cures the diſtempers of a troubled Mind: What ſhall I ſay, How ſhall I thank the dear Fountain of all my Joy and Pleaſure? 'Twas laſt night I received the Bliſs, 'tis this Night, Darling, that I pay my Thanks; let ſuch a diſtribution of my time ever be my Fate; Let me ever be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or acknowledging Benefits from that place, which makes the leaſt Favour more materially my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, than the greateſt elſewhere; Ah deareſt, ask me again and agan, when you ſhall ſee <hi>Orantes,</hi> do ſend me a thouſand ſuch Queſtions, I'le anſwer them in a thouſand— when you'll permit me to ſee you; till then I'le only ſay I ſee nothing elſe,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:99072:21"/>that can divert me, I have juſt ſight enough to conduct me from one trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to another: Thus the kind Turtle parted from his Mate, paſſes by a thouſand Objects, and only mourns at all he ſees; but met, their Joy, their Life and Love are through each others Bill conveyed. Deareſt <hi>Aſteria,</hi> give me one quarter of an hour, ſit down and write all that Love inſpires, ſhew me its ſtrength in that kind Glaſs, it may flatter, and yet be like, That Art our fineſt Painters ſtudy, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour now ſet off the Features, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible my ſweeteſt, fineſt <hi>Aſteria</hi> to Treat thee ſo; nay, contrarywiſe How dull a Rogue ſhould I be, if I were call'd to Limn thee ſo, all I can ſay, can never tell the World, how much thou deſerveſt my Paſſion, and my Duty, nor how much I love; but whither could I flye? to thy Arms I cannot? What matters then my poor remove? But not to be too trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, I will only add the firm reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I have made, that as long as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven endues me with Reaſon and Sence, I will love <hi>Aſteria,</hi> and nothing elſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:99072:22"/>I wiſh my Period and a Thought, contrary to this, may have one and the ſame Moment. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>X.</head>
               <p>THey that court Contemplation moſt, cannot brag of being more obliged by Her and all her Helps, than I, when I was laſt forc'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair to her for ſome aſſiſtance, againſt thoſe misfortunes which began to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack me, when I was driven from that place, which neither compariſon nor expreſſion will permit me to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe; the time, deareſt <hi>Delia</hi> obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged me with all the quiet, the Emb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lems of Death afford, Silence, Night, and the general retirement of all; but <hi>Poli,</hi> would have eaſily fed an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Fancy, that he had all the World to himſelf; the Stars were full as bright as thoſe which wandring <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillo</hi> changed for his Miſtriſs's want of Love; The Birds that <hi>Dion</hi> curſt, for hindring Thought were all at reſt; nay, Earth it ſelf had got ſo ſoft a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering, my Horſe could make no noiſe.
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99072:22"/>Ah Deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> How do you think I ſpent the Night? or rather can you think it poſſible that the Beauties and the Charms I quitted, and the Paſſion I brought away, could make me ſpend it otherwiſe than I did; Bleſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence that made Thought not only the beſt argument of Man's living, but the beſt way to diſtinguiſh him from other parts of Created matter. I Thought indeed, and in that world of Thought, 'twas only <hi>Delia</hi> liv'd, and ſhe appeared from thence as ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtible, as unparall'd. I did not long enjoy the pleaſing Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the one, without the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere one of the other; thoſe very Powers which made her inevitable, rendred her alſo inacceſſible; all the conſiderable occurrences of my life, ſince that moment, I had the preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or rather the neceſſity of telling ſweet <hi>Delia</hi> that I lov'd, repaſſed the track of Thought, through which they had gone; gueſs then how many Storms I had within, which all the calm without could not allay, but fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity being ſo perfectly oppoſite to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:99072:23"/>what is paſt, I muſt not expect to ſupport the one, with what may ſerve the other; give me leave therefore to tell you, that death being infinitely my deſire before life, without my love for <hi>Delia,</hi> that Paſſion muſt be unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſibly miſerable without her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Ah Madam, I were unworthy and falſe to my own Reaſon, if I ſhould not ſay, your Favour is ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable; but ſince Heaven it ſelf is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainable, May I not lay at your feet all the Service, all the Juſtice, and all the Fidelity, which Love, Merit and Gratitude have made irrevocable, and beg your leave, that theſe humble Emiſſaries may in my abſence, make uſe of their interceſſion; I know they offer nothing which comes not alſo (like Tribute to the Sea) from nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous ſtreams; But Juſt as well as Great, they who can leaſt capitulate, have moſt reaſon to be protected.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Thus petty States are öft preſerved</l>
                  <l>When greater Kingdoms are denied,</l>
                  <l>Where is your Mercy, if deſerved,</l>
                  <l>Or Power, when a Title's tried.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99072:23"/>
               <head>XI.</head>
               <p>SInce a Power above my own wiſhes, Deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> permits me not to chuſe my own Happineſs, I am forced to think it one to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound for ſuch as I may hope to receve thus being now denied ſeeking for pleaſures as innumerable as there are Beauties in <hi>Delia</hi>'s Eyes; I muſt beg of my Charmer to tranſcribe them from that Copy; indeed I may not only read the Beauties of her Perſon, but the Ornaments of her Mind. I know not how kindly ſhe may deſign to uſe me in the deſcription of the the one, but the other muſt he natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and I cannot but confeſs, nay, bind it with an Oath, that in abſence I always found the power of <hi>Delia</hi>'s Wit, enough to Eternize my Love and Reſpect, without any reflections upon her Face, and I muſt as firmly vow, That whenever I had the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make my Senſes my Judges, I always thought it ſufficient to be under the Dominion of her Eyes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:99072:24"/>without conſidering the Beauties of her Mind. But ſince I have heard of thoſe who have been reproved for entertaining charming <hi>Delia</hi> upon this Subject, I ſhall only ſay, that it is not the firſt time my Love hath ſubmitted to my Obedience. Ah, deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> let me hear from you, for I long to have ſome of thoſe new Delights re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, which this kind of Converſe affords; Who can love as <hi>Pol.</hi> doth, and not ſeek to redreſs the miſeries of Abſence? Who that loſeth the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of one Senſe, ſeeks not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge another? Who that is obliged to Thought for the greateſt part of his Content, can live without ſeeking it ſome ſubſiſtance where Paſſion and Friendſhip meet; the integrity of the one obtains a Pardon for the other; What, fine <hi>Delia</hi> may not approve from her Lover, ſhe may from her Friend: and it being yet diſputable on which ſide the exceſs lies; ſure where they both joyn, you muſt leſs doubt the truth, than I your recepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> they both ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thize in the Meſſage, and both beg of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99072:24"/>you to think upon poor <hi>Pol.</hi> And to conclude, he thinks of nothing but you: believe him in abſence as miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, as he believes <hi>Delia</hi> meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, dreaming and reſolving upon nothing but his Fidelity and his Love; both theſe, Madam, ſhall take their meaſures from your directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Oh, do but ſay how I ever can or ſhall ſerve you, and I will a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times ſooner diſpute being Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py than Obedient, <hi>Polierchus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>XII.</head>
               <p>IF to all my Affliction I muſt meet with the addition of being ſo miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreted, as to have the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that life attributed to me, which Heaven knows I would preſerve with the loſs of my own, I have then ſcarce another misfortune to look for, nor indeed, ſhould want one to diſpatch me, were I not in Reaſon as well as Opinion convinced, that upon conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration I ſhall be acquitted by that very breath that accuſed me; pray conſider whether ſuch a condition be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:99072:25"/>conſiſtent with what I have offered, if nothing elſe will do, think whether laying down every thing but my Soul to ſerve <hi>Delia,</hi> can have in it the thought of her prejudice; all this is at her ſervice every hour of the day, but a thouſand Worlds ſhould never be my temptation for a days ſorrow to her; give me not therefore this new wound, and throw that which is tenderer to me than my Eye, or my Heart; Ah charming <hi>De.</hi> heal all theſe by believing I love you with a Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion above that of Authorities, as you might do all my other miſeries, if you thought I deſerved the Cure; No <hi>Delia,</hi> live, and live as the fineſt, the worthieſt, and, the moſt charming Woman alive ought to do, and with this aſſurance, that whenever I muſt wade through a Sea of Miſeries and Afflictions, nay, to death, to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to that happy condition you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, by all that's Sacred I'le do it; having ſaid this, and vow'd once more by the Eternal Powers, that I will perform it, I will ſay no more. And now give me leave to tell you, that
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:99072:25"/>all kinds of Obedience, being as much your due as any ones, I will try what I can to live to ſerve you, till you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the other; yes, I will ſerve you with ſuch Reſpect, with ſuch Paſſion, and ſuch Care, as neither you nor the World ſhall call me in queſtion; Ah <hi>Delia;</hi> With what Tranſport did I find out that word <hi>Hope</hi> in your Letter, I know I perverted it to Senſes you never meant, it was but a ſhort Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent I enjoyed by it, therefore pray forgive me, but in its moſt limited Senſe I muſt acquaint you, that it gave me more redreſs than all the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in Town could do; truly I muſt confeſs, I was in a condition very dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from what I am in at this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moment; and tho' I try to recover, only that my relapſe may be more dangerous, I will nevertheleſs obey you as faſt as I can, and ſhall long of all things to hear, whether it be in my caſe better than Sacrifice; Bleſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels hover about you, and if it be true, that as faithful Guardians they inſpire Dreams for our direction; may they infuſe into your Soul, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:99072:26"/>and humble Paſſion I have for you, <hi>Delia</hi> will then know that no Mortal had ever more obedience than I, nor more power than <hi>Delia;</hi> make uſe of it, Madam, as you pleaſe, till Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in my laſt Tragedy incapacitate me, you ſhall never fail of ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as the greateſt Merit, and the greateſt Love muſt neceſſarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>XIII.</head>
               <p>YOu muſt be ſo abundantly ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, not only of the Notion I have of Happineſs, but of the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation I have laid of all I wiſh in this World, that it is impoſſible you ſhould think <hi>Call.</hi> the perſon you repreſent him. Beſides, knowing, fine <hi>Methri.</hi> ſo generous as to have ſome kind of content in making others happy. I am naturally led to the ſad Reflections of my own Imperfections; when I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire for a reaſon, why I ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be ſo unjuſtly and unkindly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted: Oh Madam, How can you ſay that the declaration of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:99072:26"/>for charming <hi>Methri.</hi> would have lookt like the Sentiments of my Heart; but that you can never be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what I have made my whole buſineſs to convince you of: Beſtow a moment, I beg of you, to conſider, whether I were capable of ſaying the one, ſo long as Heaven Bleſt me with my Reaſon and my Sence; and think whether I deſerve to have the other ſaid to me; believe it, <hi>I</hi> have had no ſuch pleaſure ſince <hi>I</hi> ſee you laſt, as to want this allay, nor ſo unmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of what is now the inſeparable at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant of my life, as to merit this reproach. But how can you force your Reaſon to make ſuch a conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſomething elſe <hi>I</hi> ſaid; as to conclude, <hi>I</hi> have taken ſuch pains to deface that <hi>Idea,</hi> which is ſo infinitely preferible before any other object, 'tis true, <hi>I</hi> ſaid ſince <hi>I</hi> admired you, and before you knew it; amongſt other attempts <hi>I</hi> reſolved to try the Philoſophy of expelling Fire by Fire; but having given you an account of the ſucceſs then, <hi>I</hi> wonder you could infer any thing but the contrary of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:99072:27"/>what you did: Since that Bleſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherein you deigned to know you were in my Thoughts the fineſt Woman living; <hi>I</hi> hope you do not expect <hi>I</hi> ſhould give you Thanks for the obliging aſſiſtance you ſo readily offer me, or that in ſavour of your kind proteſtation, <hi>I</hi> ſhould this Poſt, according to your deſire, ſend you word, <hi>I</hi> am in want of your help; no Madam, <hi>I</hi> muſt tell you, that all the Trials you can find, not all the Charms of the Sex, not all the power of <hi>Call.</hi> can make me endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, deſire, or think of ſo great baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or ſo much misfortune without horror; imagine then how infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you have afflicted one that loves the ground you tread on, one that would lay his Fortune and his Life, as he hath done his Love at your Feet, to obtain your Favour or Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief; But how impoſſible is it for me to enjoy theſe Bleſſings under the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy condition of Abſence, where Malice, Emulation, and that ready Inclination that always waits upon you to make the ſevereſt and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:99072:27"/>Interpretation of whatever I can ſay or write, will ſtill render me unfortunate. Well, ſweeteſt <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatia</hi> live, aſſured whatever Fate attends me in this unparallel'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern, it ſhall be the laſt of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that ſhall ever poſſeſs my Soul, and that as you may ſecure me with all delight imaginable, whatever Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Reverence, or Fidelity made any Man, ſo under all misfortunes, you ſhall never diveſt me of theſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves; adieu, if you will throw one Thought upon the greateſt Fidelity in being; Let me not waſte my tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous hours away in trouble of this kind, but ſend poor <hi>Call.</hi> ſome ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as have often fill'd his Heart with Joy, in return you ſhall be preſented with treaſures of Love and Reſpect in a Heart ſo full of Obedience, as ſhall make you as abſolute in your power, as you are in your Merit. Adieu, Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99072:28"/>
               <head>XIV.</head>
               <p>SInce the pleaſures of poor <hi>Orantes</hi> increaſe with the health of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Aſteria,</hi> How do you think he is engaged for every moments care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to preſerve it; I know he is eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day making it his buſineſs to requite the Obligation, and if I am not mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, or rather too ſhort liv'd, I fancy I ſhall live to ſee dear <hi>Aſteria</hi> convinced; Love, Friendſhip and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity, are the Ballaſt of his Soul; Ah Madam, they carry his little Pinnace ſteady through all Storms and all Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates, and when he parts with them, may his Veſſel ſink, I long now for the happy time, but that ſubmiſſion which always guides me, is not now to fail me; well fine <hi>Aſteria,</hi> Nature hath no ſtronger ties, no not thoſe that hold the World together, than thoſe that keep the faithful <hi>Orantes</hi> in your ſervice, and you in the Heart of him, there it is you reign ſolely, that little Monarchy, adorable <hi>Aſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> is your own; it is not in the power
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:99072:28"/>of Humane race to hinder it, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but death can dethrone you; Yes <hi>Aſteria,</hi> By the Eternal Powers 'tis true, and may I dye poor, unpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied and without friend, when I am perjured, or break rhe Vows I have call'd Heaven and all its Angels to witneſs to; no dear <hi>Aſteria, Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> would be the moſt inhumane, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and unjuſteſt of Mankind (the inferences from which will make up the greateſt Impoſture living) if he could admit a ſecond Love to triumph there, then why may not the more powerful, and the more meritorious <hi>Aſteria,</hi> love as well, and as long as <hi>Orantes,</hi> when once 'twas vowed; Why doth not that Law of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians</hi> tie the one as well as the other; Ah <hi>Aſteria,</hi>
                  <q>
                     <l>You can't, you muſt be none but mine,</l>
                     <l>And may I periſh, when I am not wholly thine.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99072:29"/>
               <head>XV.</head>
               <p>I Am, deareſt <hi>Methridatia,</hi> ſaith a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcellanie of Paſſions rais'd by hope of that tendereſt compaſſion which ſo ſurround <hi>Delia.</hi> and ſo depreſt by fear of my own demerits, that being unaccountable to my ſelf, it cannot be ſuppoſed I ſhould give any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to charming <hi>Meth.</hi> than that I love in ſpight of all thoſe Calms and Tempeſts, whoſe ſuſpence is a freſh torment; Ah ſweet <hi>Meth.</hi> if I am to hear ſuch news as will bring all the joys and quiet that can keep me alive, or can allay a thouſand terrors, let me not be denied one minute from you, to inlarge upon <hi>Delia</hi>'s reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether ſhe will depend upon <hi>Pol.</hi> for her Content, and Happineſs, as he doth upon her for his Life, and every Breath he draws. But if inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orable Fate dooms me to more than I can expreſs; and <hi>Delia</hi> gives up her ſelf to another, that ſhe may own her Conqueſt to the World; a little will ſerve to gueſs at what involves him
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:99072:29"/>unſuitable Sorrow, and what, I think will carry me to my Grave; Oh <hi>Methridatia, Delia</hi> is your Friend, perſwade her I may live; tell her, 'tis pity ſuch a maſs of Love and Faith ſhould be hurried to the lower Shades; tell her I will be her Skreen at Noon day, to keep her from the heat and violence of the Sun, and at night my Eyes ſhall keep a ſtrict watch to guard her from the evils may happen; Do <hi>Methridatia</hi> tell her all this, and let me tell you, if ever Paper were attended with wiſhes violent enough to force ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; this comes ſtored with enough, indeedi as many as ever the proſpect of the greateſt Bliſs or Terror of the higheſt Miſery, extorted from the Breaſt of Mortal. Adieu. For till I hear I have no more power to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a word to any other Subject, than Misfortune hath to make <hi>Pol.</hi> alter his Faith and Love, that is to be his longeſt companion on Earth; wit that (let <hi>Delia</hi> uſe him as ſhe pleaſe) He reſolves to ſtemn all Tides, being aſſured as he can never be happy
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:99072:30"/>without it, ſo can he never be ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable as to be diveſted of that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in the moſt unhappy condition.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>If <hi>Delia</hi> gives me a Reprieve,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be be Bleſt, and wiſh to Live.</l>
                  <l>Yet <hi>Delia,</hi> 'tis not fit I die;</l>
                  <l>I'le live, and ſhare thy Deſtinie.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>XVI.</head>
               <p>IF ſo mean an aſſiſtance as that of wiſhes could contribute to the Happineſs of the meritorious <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia,</hi> there are enough ſent her by the Humble <hi>Call.</hi> for a <hi>Newyears</hi>-gift, to make her Bleſt to ſuch degrees, as her Thoughts cannot reach. Mental Services have always been the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant offerings of the greateſt Lovers, and Heaven hath always placed them amongſt the prime Oblations; but on Earth there is a material difference that attends, not our Sacrifices to thoſe above, for there the Mind of them that pay, ſet a value upon what they pay; But here it is the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them that receive that, ſtamps
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:99072:30"/>the Eſtimation, which being ſo, I dare not preſume to lay a greater claim to the merit of what I offer, than what ſweet <hi>Methridatia</hi> will permit, and that I fear depending upon the Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor this may find her in; I can but make very uncertain meaſures of what will be its ſate; it comes charming <hi>Methri.</hi> to let you ſee, I will begin this as I ended the laſt year, and to beg you will give me leave to make this proteſtation, That nothing but death ſhall hinder me from performing theſe ſervices, or any other I can pay you as ſucceſſive as the years of my life; nothing comes incompaſſed with ſuch advantage, ſurrounded with ſuch Glory and Beauty as can divert my Thoughts, or looks one moment; no <hi>Meth</hi> know that I—</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Without a change or taking turn,</l>
                  <l>Only for you in ſilence burn,</l>
                  <l>Let your ſound Reaſon judge for me,</l>
                  <l>You'l ſee I can no others be,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs deſign'd for Miſery. <hi>Adieu.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99072:31"/>
               <head>XVII.</head>
               <p>YOu ſeem'd ſweet <hi>Methridatia</hi> ſo inclinable to oblige me with the favour of your Note, as I could not but think you extremely unkind, to be ſo hardly perſwaded to what I have often told you is ſo great a pleaſure: But I begin to think you were in it more generous than at that time I apprehended; and that knowing how many things in the World diſcontent me, you declined giving me the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of increaſing their number; if therefore my importunity drew upon me the misfortune, I confeſs my ſelf properly chargeable, yet I cannot but ſay, there was a great deal of cruelty in the Fancy that dictated, and in the Hand that inflicted ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a Sentence, as with ſo much Wit, and ſo little Kindneſs you ſhrouded under the ſeeming Obligation of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: Oh <hi>Methridatia,</hi> Do you think it is ten thouſand to one, but ſome new Object will come to deface the Impreſſions you have fixt in my mind,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:99072:31"/>and that rather than fail, I ſhall be rifling my Memory to recall the <hi>Idea</hi> of ſomething that may be agreeable enough to divert my Thoughts; Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity, Madam, could deſign, nor In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity deſerve no more; if you real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believe me this Man, or if I am ſo, I unworthily aggravate my Crimes by the preſumption of coming near you, and ought to die; and if you think me not ſo, I am made too unhappy in your Expreſſion; But too charming and too unkind <hi>Methridatia,</hi> was it not enough to render me odious to my ſelf, but from the faults I will ſooner expire than act, to lay a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for the liberty you are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to take; Ask, ſweet—whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not too much, I dare ſwear, ſhe will ſay it is probable my Misfortunes may, my Guilt will never oblige you with ſuch a freedom; But if it may be allowable to anſwer for my ſelf, let me ſay, if either a part or future proſpect could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed ſo far upon my imagination, as to have appeared under a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of redreſſing my misfortunes, I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:99072:32"/>have not had more reaſon than time to put it in execution; Flattery or Change, Madam, never found way into my Soul, ſince that fatal time of renouncing my own Power, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting to Time, <hi>Mithridatia;</hi> I was never beholden to the hopes of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs for thoſe reſolutions my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon obliged me with, in preferring you before the race of Woman-kind, nor was I ever frighted with the Image of my ſufferings from one of thoſe Vows, by which I have united thoſe various emotions that too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hinder our conſiderations in what we undertake; without arrogating therefore to my ſelf, I am as ſure as our condition on this ſide Heaven will admit, that no exterior Object can dethrone my Sence, my Reaſon, and my Reſolution to make room for any diverſions, except ſuch as reſult from the contemplation of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thridatia</hi>'s Merit; I am therefore, Madam, with or without your permiſſion, under a fate impoſſible to be removed from, in point of Opinion, and as unalte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in Practice, If ſweet <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia</hi>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99072:32"/>would think the Service and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of my Life were a fit offering to be accepted. <hi>I</hi> am reſolv'd to find a way to take my leave to Morrow in the Evening, in hopes you will not be ſo willing to Manumiſs one that courts h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Chains, before the Liberty to you ſo eaſily give; and who in ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence knows no other pleaſure than to contemplate upon thoſe Delights he had in ſeeing <hi>Methridatia</hi> laſt. Adieu Soul of my Soul, never to be diminiſhed by time or misfortune in the thought of poor <hi>Callimiches.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <head>XVIII.</head>
               <p>IF you be convinced, your Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Misfortune depends upon the Paſſion and Reſpect that is paid you by <hi>Call.</hi> pray conclude upon the firſt, if it be poſſible for him to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it, for <hi>I</hi> here call all that is powerful to atteſt this Proteſtation. that rather than make you miſerable, <hi>I</hi> will not only quit my Delight, but my Life. Nor do <hi>I</hi> think the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment ſuch as to make you ſcruple
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:99072:33"/>its belief; for if all the pleaſure of my days conſiſts in the Love I pay you, What reaſon have I to wiſh the length of that time, which doth but but give me a duration to my ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, in making that which is as dear as my Soul, unhappy; I am now paſt all thoſe doubts which attend new taken up Paſſions; I muſt love you, but that Love will make me wiſh my end, rather than your misfortune. Oh <hi>Methri.</hi> it is but your reſolving to make us both happy, and we will be ſo; if poor Mortals are not delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their Belief, nothing creates it but Love and Fidelity: And I do here invoke Heaven to puniſh me with all the Afflictions the <hi>Aegyptians</hi> ever knew, when I ceaſe loving my admired <hi>Methridatia,</hi> or break thoſe Vows I have made to ſerve her, till I am no more; Yes, <hi>Methridatia</hi> may, and Sufferings be my Eternal Reward when I love you not, as now I tell you; we ſhould be too happy could you love the faithful <hi>Calamiches</hi> halfe ſo well. Adieu.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99072:33"/>
               <q>
                  <l>When thirſty Feavors ſcorch up all our Blood,</l>
                  <l>We Dream of Rivers drinking up a Flood.</l>
                  <l>When we are prey'd upon by fierce deſire,</l>
                  <l>We quench not, but are adding to the fire,</l>
                  <l>An abſent Love hath torments of each kind,</l>
                  <l>Deſtroys the Body, Macerates the Mind.</l>
                  <l>Fears in their horrid ſhapes appear to fright</l>
                  <l>Diſpair, cloath'd with thick darkneſs as the Night</l>
                  <l>Permits; not hope to look through that black Veil;</l>
                  <l>Nor can our Reaſon thoſe high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſcale,</l>
                  <l>Which are between our Joys and us. Ah-Dear!</l>
                  <l>Light, that can'ſt ſcatter Miſts, make Diſtance near,</l>
                  <l>Shed thy prolifick Beams, and ſhew poor <hi>C.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That he is happy in his loving <hi>D.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99072:34"/>
               <head>XIX.</head>
               <p>DId. Sweet <hi>Aſteria</hi> know how fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful poor <hi>Orantes</hi> is of being trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome, and yet how impoſſible it is for him to reſiſt any opportunity, he would be forgiven for erring on this ſide; it would be an unſpeakable tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to him to be injurious to her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; But he hath begg'd theſe may be always laid aſide till ſome auſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous moment gives them admittance, they are truly, the only Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he hath, which gives him any content or eaſe; they unlade a part of his Sorrows by ſending them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Sence he hath of being wounded in the tendereſt part, but Heaven hath reſerved the Knowledge of our Spirits to its ſelf, for who can deſcribe Pain, or paint Sorrow in its true ſufferings, and yet there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing both ſo certain and unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in our Souls as methinks I know and ſeel my dear <hi>Aſteria</hi>'s troubles, I am ſure, I do enough to make it the greateſt Grief and Affliction that
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:99072:34"/>ever reacht my Soul; Ah, when ſhall diſconſolate <hi>Orantes</hi> hear <hi>Aſteria</hi> mends and is chearful; 'tis an Age ſince thoſe Joys arrived, but ſure you are not ſo wanting either to Heaven or your ſelf, as not to promote them to your Power; but I fear I am too long, Guards of Angels attend you, tender as my wiſhes, may my diſaſters never load you, nor my Prayers ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fail you; may all I have vowed be my Damnation, if I leave you, and may you live to be convinced beyond a doubt, that <hi>Orantes</hi> prefers his Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity before his Life. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>XX.</head>
               <p>I was not more loath to leave the ſweet Authreſs of my Joy, the night before I came away; then I was troubled not to ſee her the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, but I was ſo plagued with the diſorders and noiſe of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Excize-men, who were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out or Town, that I was forced to get up; it was like midnight when I paſſed by the Door of my Deareſt
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:99072:35"/>
                  <hi>Delia.</hi> Beſides, the Snow and the Winds were ſo exceſſive ſharp, that I was near being cured of all manner of trouble by their having taken from me the ſence of Pain; indeed I put my Face almoſt benumm'd into the weather, and can ſafely ſwear I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſelf ſuch Cold before, nor have yet recovered one of my Hands, I had that day a Conviction, that our Soul's are moſt imployed when the Body's uſeleſs, for I only knew I lived becauſe I thought; and how often did I think of the vaſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt what I enjoyed over night, and what I then wanted; that mighty diſproportion, deareſt Madam, lookt moſt diſmal, I had no charming <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatia</hi>'s Eyes to warm me, no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanting of <hi>Delia</hi>'s Tongue to allay my Grieſs, no meritorious <hi>Aſteria</hi> by me, and for an addition, that cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciating Thought, like Wild fire flew about me, for not having paid the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I both deſired and ought to do; I had all the afflictions were wiſht me by a power which can as eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict them, as ſhe can confer Bleſſings;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:99072:35"/>Ah Dear Dear, wiſh me no ill, for if you do, may this hour be my laſt, if I wiſh to proſper; you have my Life and my Happineſs, and I may ſay without preſumption, my Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion depends upon you, it being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely in your Power to make me a better or a worſe Man, as you pleaſe; Why may it not then be the firſt: Have we not often, my dear <hi>Delia,</hi> concluded ſomething in our Natures, our Humors and Reaſon ſo alike, as if Heaven had deſign'd but one Soul betwixt us; and will you not take care of your own? Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> deny it not, and you ſhall have a Life ſpent in your ſervice, the expiration of which ſhall only end it; but I muſt now leave this, and tell you I am again incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to go to <hi>London</hi> and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome things which are the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intercourſes of acquaintance, as ſuch diſdain, not to know you muſt command your faithful <hi>Pol.</hi> Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> (this is buſineſs) He hates to menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any thing in love, but what the niceſt Thought of <hi>Delia</hi> may allow from the Humble and Paſſionate <hi>Pol.</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99072:36"/>Who has not a Ieſs ſolid, tho' a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernt foundation, who has <hi>Indies,</hi> tho' not Golden ones to offer, Empires, tho' not ſo groſs as Intereſt and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition lives upon. Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> Heaven and the Powers above (of which the Mind of Man is a Type,) confirm what I ſay to you for Truth, and ſhew you the vaſt difference betwixt the laſting power of Merit, and the ſhort dominion of Deſign; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther am I falling, let ſome proſperous Gale direct my Paſſion into <hi>Delia</hi>'s Breaſt, ſweet, ſafe and happy Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, let me there unload all that Love, Fidelity, Religion and Honour ever made binding, and let <hi>Delia</hi> take choice of all <hi>I</hi> have to offer; nay, ſhe muſt refuſe none, it being the gift of Heaven as well as mine; well, Adieu, all the Bleſſings of Heaven deſcend upon you, quiet Hours, ſoft Dreams, and ſteady Friends be your Portion, and let me beg you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve none ſo much, ſo as your unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Lover <hi>Polierchus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:99072:36"/>
               <head>XXI.</head>
               <p>SInce all the ambition of my Life receiv'd its Original from, and hath its termination in fineſt <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia;</hi> How pardonable is it, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of the unjuſt diminution you make of that Merit which gave my Paſſion its Being, and is the happy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of its duration; it is of the higheſt concern poſſible to me, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige you to believe, that I think you what you are, but 'tis very ſtrange you'll not own what you know you are; 'tis yet ſome ſatisfaction to ſee what Arguments you are forced to ſupport your diffidence withal, either to reſolve I muſt be ignorant of what I make appear I know, or to diſown your own knowledge, rather than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what I vow to be true, Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Methridatia,</hi> be not any longer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious to ſo many attractions as make all can be paid your due, nor to that Love which beſides being its own de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, would in its Falſity, be my Infamy and misfortune. But conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:99072:37"/>had you not upon a long Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation been preferible to me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all the World, you had not been my choice, and had you not been that, my Paſſion had been impoſſible, now my Reaſon is its companion, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing determined by a Power which can confer what the nature of Reaſon and Love can deſire; there can be no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſſurance of its continuance, than your Favour; give me that, deareſt Madam, and believe me Juſt, and it ſhall not be in the power of Second Cauſes to violate in our Caſe, that Order which Nature in other things is ſo careful to preſerve; my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs ſhall depend upon my Love, that upon my Vows, they upon my Reaſon, and all upon <hi>Methridatia</hi>'s Merit; as the Spring, the only ſweet Fountain from whence to derive upon paſſionate <hi>Call</hi> the pleaſant moments of his Life; Call not this Folly, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, nor think it ſo eaſily alterable, at your own, or any other bodies pleaſure; for had you an equal Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation both from your Judgment and your Inclination to value <hi>Call.</hi> before
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:99072:37"/>any thing elſe; you would not know where to look for either Power or Will to reſiſt the ſweet violence of a particularity: But becauſe this Caſe is not like to arrive from the inequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity you will always find betwixt your ſelf and others; yet muſt you not by this Rule judge them, eſpecially poor <hi>Call.</hi> whoſe unhappy defects make his pretences to any right in your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs impoſſible, but yet cannot ſtop the tide of that Ambition which ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth as far as Admiration and Reſpect will admit; I cannot give you a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Inſtance of both, than when I tell you that nothing hath been more my wiſh and deſire, than your being ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied to allay the terror of Abſence with this kind of Converſe; but ſince you ſay 'tis troubleſom, and I cannot be obliged but at the expence of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſagreeable, I will endeavour to moderate the heat of thoſe impatien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which yet I cannot ſo regulate, as not to wiſh for a Note to day; But pardon me, if I err in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I pretend to repent; and indeed I fear your own Declaration looks
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:99072:38"/>too like a Civil notice, that mine are too frequent and too long, yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear ſaying, that if I have any Sence, you deſigned my making uſe of it, when you tell me, if your obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation fail not, the heat will be over by that time you return. Oh <hi>Methri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datia,</hi> it had all the Cruelty imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable in it, to anſwer for one, and pardon me if I ſay all the diſobligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and injuſtice poſſible to include the other; it carrying with it all that can conclude me miſerable or infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous: No Madam, I have not built my Paſſion upon the hopes of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, it had misfortune in proſpect, but it lookt not grim enough to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert me more from loving you to come in that State, then it did long ago under a ſuffering Silence; you cannot therefore be free from my Reſpect; however, I may be diveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of your Favour, which yet I will proſecute with a life ſo ſpent in your Service, as ſhall make you wiſh I had more Merit, to have been made more Happy. Adieu.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99072:38"/>
               <q>
                  <l>I never found, ſeeing my Love one day,</l>
                  <l>Could the Delights to morrow brings allay,</l>
                  <l>Each day produces various Joys,</l>
                  <l>And Pleaſure doth conſit in Choice;</l>
                  <l>Why then ſhould this Converſe which muſt ſupply</l>
                  <l>The Powers of Sence meet a worſe deſtiny,</l>
                  <l>It ceaſes to be Love or Joy, when we,</l>
                  <l>Ceaſe wiſhing them Eternity.</l>
                  <l>Down Rebel Fear, the Juſt <hi>Aſteria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The pleaſant Charming <hi>Methridatia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The fine, the ſweet the generous <hi>Delia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will not refuſe the Duty that I pay</l>
                  <l>Becauſe 'twas humbly paid them yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</l>
                  <l>Abſence that preys on Thought when this Relief</l>
                  <l>Cannot be had, turn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all to Fear and Grief.</l>
                  <l>Now Love and Hope at work Command in Chief.</l>
                  <l>By theſe two Meſſengers be pleas'd to know,</l>
                  <l>That Streams do not more naturally flow</l>
                  <l>To their dear Ocean, then my Soul to you</l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99072:39"/>
                  <l>That Sweets from Flowers, perſum'd Gums from Tree,</l>
                  <l>That Virgin Honey from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>den Bee,</l>
                  <l>Are not ſo ſweet as one kind Look from <hi>D.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>XXII.</head>
               <p>IT is not my charming <hi>Delia</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a mixture of all thoſe appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions which make up the greateſt Concern, that I ever now receive the Honour of a Letter, the Joy to ſee it, and the fear to find in it any thing ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inous to my Love, are always endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to ſupplant one another, and truly I cannot but ſay I found enough couched under a ſerious and grave ſtile to ſet my Fears on work; for dear <hi>Delia,</hi> ſhould it proceed from a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of my Love (as ſure thus many years has convinced you I can never change) I will waſte away this wretched Life in deſpair; Yes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if my Vows and Oaths, which Heaven only knows I have made, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thoſe I have paid at your Feet, will not ſecure you to this Breaſt, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:99072:39"/>perſwade you I will carry this Paſſion to my Grave, I am not ſitting to live; Alas, to break with you would be barbarous, inhumane and baſe, I am not arrived at ſuch Villanies yet, and when I do, let my end come, or what is worſe, be every Man's wonder. Then give me leave to hope you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, and to ſend you a Vow ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from the bottom my Soul, ſent with a Paſſion and Fidelity inferior to none I ever read of, that if you will keep me alive and give me leave to love you, it ſhall never violate the Rules you ſet to your own Goodneſs and my Duty, nor ever know decay till <hi>Pol.</hi> His great one, Ah deareſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> believe poor <hi>Po.</hi> that is ready to dye for Love and Grief, to read a melancholy Letter, let me implore you not to queſtion my Faith; but to conclude me as unalterable as the decrees of Heaven; come <hi>Delia,</hi> the Sun will yet ſhine, and we ſhall yet live to appear our ſelves. Charge not your ſelf for not ſearching the World, nor do not lay ſuch Corro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſives as too many of them will cauſe
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:99072:40"/>the death of the paſſionate <hi>Poli.</hi> Adieu Soul of my Soul.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>I Love thee more than Miſers do their Wealth,</l>
                  <l>Than Captives Freedom, or than ſick Men Health.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <head>XXIII.</head>
               <p>I Was in ſuch great hopes that the Saturdays Poſt would have brought ſome account of <hi>Delia</hi>'s Health, as poor <hi>Po.</hi> hath waſted his whole Day with expectation and wiſhes, but the Poſt is come and no news; if it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned as a continued piece of ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Po.</hi> ſubmits. But ſince he cannot but dread every accident which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders his hearing when dear <hi>Delia</hi> is not well; it may eaſily be gueſſed how uneaſie he is, all his Treaſure is in one bottom, and how natural, at leaſt how frequent is it, to make the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of a ruine, almoſt as great as the ruine it ſelf; indeed <hi>Po.</hi> is extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned as ever I ſaw him in my life; Alas, he is ſo far from omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:99072:40"/>any opportunity of ſending, as were the conveniencies every hour of the day I dare ſay, <hi>Delia</hi> would miſs very few, for he ſpends them all in thinking of his Deareſt; and his only Concern. Truly all the tenderneſs that the Soul of Man hath, is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, when we fear for that dear Friend; you muſt let me ſome way or other, know how you are, or torment me to death; order ſome body to write two words, for I would not have you venture your Eyes yet: But alas, what do I talk, you may be dead, you may be any thing, I have not heard theſe three Poſts; Ah how wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly miſerable has this made me, if ſatal this arrives, farewel to Joy with as much reſolution, as I will welcome Death, which the Holy one knows I will do whenever I loſe my <hi>Delia;</hi> I was in hopes the worſt had been paſt, when <hi>I</hi> left you, and if ſo, Why do <hi>I</hi> not hear from you; remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber what Grief and Sorrow plunged me into at the beginning of this great misfortune, you know <hi>I</hi> am but juſt recovered, and if you have a mind to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99072:41"/>defer my death, have a care of the moſt deſerving of Women, for 'tis to her alone my Services and my Life are Dedicated; Fidelity is not more your due, than 'tis my nature, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whatever Calumnies from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice or Ignorance <hi>I</hi> may lie under, you can anſwer for me for many years: <hi>I</hi> pray take it here for an undeniable Truth, bound with all the reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vows and Reſolutions my Soul can make, that only at the Feet of my charming <hi>Delia</hi> will <hi>I</hi> breath out my Love and my Obedience in my laſt breath; my Love ſhall end with my Life, and when that goes my Eyes ſhall cloſe up the Image of my Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Delia;</hi> Let me hear, <hi>I</hi> beſeech you, as ſoon as poſſible, for if ever uncertainty was pain, it is now a tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, an unſpeakable one to me; Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> What did <hi>I</hi> not leave you well, and of ſuch a Diſeaſe, how cruel is the mention of it? Why did not Fate permit <hi>Po.</hi> to bear the burthen; <hi>I</hi> repent the word, for <hi>I</hi> ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem it one, tho' it were my deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: Ah think how loth <hi>I</hi> am
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99072:41"/>ſay Farewel to all that is my Joy, and all that is my Life. Adieu.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Witneſs this Truth for me, ye Rural Powers,</l>
                  <l>Such as inhabit Groves, or ſit in Bowers.</l>
                  <l>You watry Nymphs, and ſuch as dwell in Shade.</l>
                  <l>How oft to you was this confeſſion made?</l>
                  <l>Witneſs you nimble Spirits of the Air,</l>
                  <l>And you its Quire who ſing away your Care.</l>
                  <l>I tried as many years as moſt have lov'd</l>
                  <l>To ſave the Heart, hath ſo defenceleſs prov'd</l>
                  <l>But as ſome Warlike Nation grown too great,</l>
                  <l>And numerous for its Native fertile Seat;</l>
                  <l>Sends Colonies abroad to diſpoſſeſs</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who made Home-bred Eaſe their Happineſs.</l>
                  <l>Too much confined, tho' in vaſt Empire She</l>
                  <l>Conquers no leſs than general Liberty</l>
                  <l>Such Force victorions <hi>Delia</hi> did diſplay,</l>
                  <l>Night could as well reſiſt the approaching Day.</l>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:99072:42"/>
                  <l>Yet have we ſeen a thickned watry Cloud,</l>
                  <l>Sometimes attempt to be the Morning Shroud,</l>
                  <l>And as the mighty ſpreading light begun,</l>
                  <l>Tried to withſtand the luſtre of the Sun,</l>
                  <l>Suce weak attempts hath Reaſon ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times made,</l>
                  <l>But how like Clouds did oppoſition fade.</l>
                  <l>Tell her, Oh tell her, ye Powers above,</l>
                  <l>I am made up of Duty and of Love.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>XXIV.</head>
               <p>DId you know how valuable every little is that comes from the Head and Hand of fineſt <hi>Methrida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia,</hi> there would have been more care taken, than to have let ſo great a part of that little, ſuffer Martyrdom before it came to Tryal: Nay, having made <hi>Call.</hi> Judge, I am ſure the execution had been deferr'd till they had been companions in deſtruction; But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member you are accountable to me for the Ruine of what <hi>I</hi> eſteem above the value of anything, but ſuch an reparation as you can make, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:99072:42"/>now ſo fair an opportunity of appealing to your generoſity; think not I have ſo much as to loſe it; nay, had I as much as generous <hi>Methridatia</hi> her ſelf, <hi>I</hi> ſhould dare intrench upon what ſhe prizeth ſo much, or rob her of ſo great a ſhare, as ſhe hath now occaſion for; Know then the thirſty Earth was never more cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous; nay, that I have in this caſe a Soul ſo great, as not to be contented with leſs, than what the Nobleſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon living can give in compenſation, for what was almoſt ineſtimable; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect me therefore to come and dun you. I ſhould not be in a condition to have entertained any one ſo much at random upon this Subject, if I had not been laſt night bleſt with the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py news of a friend of mine being recovered of a Diſtemper I dreaded, a perſon ſo dear to me; by all that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and obligation can inſpire, as I muſt beg of you to congratulate with me; Oh! Compariſons are odious, yet I muſt ſay, that neither <hi>Methridatia</hi> nor <hi>Delia,</hi> (both whom I am ſure you admire) put together, have more Charms, ſhe
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99072:43"/>hath as well the awful Grandure of the one, as the more gentle attracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the other: She hath the ſmart Wit of one, as well as the ſweet and converſible temper of the other; ſhe wants not thoſe Beauties that variety in Humor gives the one, nor thoſe ſeveral Graces wherein the particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the other abounds; that mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious kind of negligent Charm in one, which makes all ſorts of Perſons and Tempers follow her, whilſt it neither looks like pain or deſign in her: nor that irreſiſtible Power in the other, which never yet fail'd her whenever ſhe deſign'd it, either for Bliſs or Puniſhment, have not in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind made them more conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; then this friend of mine who hath that eaſie unexpenſive, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witching Civility of the one, which makes every one doubt, whether their Happineſs or her Kindneſs be poſſible; and that more peculiar ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage in her particular converſe which in the other, makes the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Fidelity ſhe would preſerve inviolabe. Oh Madam, no attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99072:43"/>or admired quality in the Soul of either of theſe, exceeds what my friend enjoys; nay, there is ſo great a reſemblance as would you give me incouragement, I ſhould not deſpair of pleaſing you upon this Subject; ſince the Picture I ſhould give you of my own, would be almoſt the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of your two Friends, who ſeem to be both born to be like mine; for ſhe hath the fine Hair and Eyes of one, the ſweet moild Shape and Mien of the other, Motion and Cloaths are as much her Friends, as ſhe is happy in defiance of both. Negligence or Deſign being ever thought beſt, as ſhe is found in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but I begin to fear you will think me as fond of the Parallel as of my Friend, and doubt whether I love yours or my own beſt, and if ſo, I am in ſome hope alſo, that you will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſuſpect your ſelf, and truly I think not without reaſon, for if in ſweet <hi>Aſteria</hi> you can find all the Charms, that are in <hi>Methridatia</hi> and <hi>Delia,</hi> Why ſhould you not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to contract what now you are
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:99072:44"/>forc'd to divide; but if not, I will propoſe this, That I will promiſe to gain you all the Friendſhip and Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt imaginable in mine, if you will endeavour to ſet me firm in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and eſteem of your Friends; Oh did you, or would you know the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſuch a Converſe; this little parcel of Friends, with almoſt any misfortunes elſe were more preſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than what the World in great miſtake, beſides Calls great and pleaſant; the thought of it makes my Cell a Paradiſe, its enjoyments ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits no parallel; Adieu, I do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to take your forgiving this for any part of the recompence I expect, for the uſing Wit, and may be kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the <hi>Romans</hi> did the Bodies of diſeaſed Friends; theirs was Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Interrment, yours was Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>XXV.</head>
               <p>IT is no wonder if all that ever repreſented it ſelf, obligatory to the Mind of Man, appears with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99072:44"/>when it comes under the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of my Love, for this great Merit and great Paſſion may have been your Obſervation; yet it is ſo ſeldom that theſe are ſupported by founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, great as any of themſelves, that poor <hi>Po.</hi> may not only Bleſs his own Fate, but ſurely convince deareſt <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> that if a ſence of having been ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Honour, the higheſt Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons Intereſt and Friendſhip can Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize the Thoughts of a Gentleman; He may then ſay, change, misfortune, or ambition can no more dethrone the Sweet, the Charming Image of my Adored <hi>Delia</hi> from the Soul of <hi>Po:</hi> then the Giants, (thoſe Monſters of Earth,) could <hi>Jupiter</hi> from Heaven; no, <hi>Delia</hi> is there; neither can the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of moſt proſperous or adverſe condition make her leſs abſolute. To this I ſign the pureſt part of that Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity Heaven endued me with, to you, oh deareſt <hi>Delia,</hi> I ſend as many and more Sighs than here are Letters; a croud of Thoughts and Wiſhes inſpire my paſſionate Soul; Yet I muſt keep within bounds:
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:99072:45"/>So adieu, Million of Bleſſings ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <head>XXVI.</head>
               <p>ALas Dear <hi>Aſteria,</hi> to ſay <hi>Orantes</hi> loves, is but to ſay he lives, and to own its due to <hi>Aſteria,</hi> and the Obligations ſhe hath conferred, is but to ſay I have not loſt my reaſon, and that I am not the baſeſt of Men; truly I boaſt not, but <hi>I</hi> rejoyce that Gratitude and Fidelity are as inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable from my Life, as Life from my Soul; Where is the place, What doth <hi>Orantes</hi> do, that makes your diffidence his misfortune? Ah <hi>Aſteria,</hi> examine all your unkindneſs can ſuggeſt? Think how it is poſſible for him to be unjuſt, whoſe Fidelity by being his recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence is to be his happineſs; beſides, is not <hi>Aſteria</hi> my deliberately choſen Object, have I not in a croud, as well as in private, ſworn, no Man's choice was ſo well fitted to his Mind? Ah Madam, I muſt loſe the name of Man, and turn to that of Beaſt, whenever any temptation or bait fetch tha Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:99072:45"/>from my Soul, or one ſpark of it from my Breaſt, which I have ſworn to you: No, <hi>Aſteria,</hi> my preferring you before all the World, has only made me wiſh to have my Life pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed; thoſe only being the darling Moments of my time, that are ſpent in <hi>Aſteria</hi>'s Favour, and Service; then conclude, no exchange, no barter for ſuch Joys, whenever I do, may I break, grow wretched, and dye unpittied. Adieu.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>XXVII.</head>
               <p>THE Bleſſings of a Favour from my delightful <hi>Aſteria,</hi> is ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect a reward for all my ſufferings, as I loſe all my reſentments and forget being unhappy whenever ſhe preſents to my view, the dear Paper filled with Kindneſs and Wit. But why ſhould I ſay this, methinks it is like thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you for miſſing the firſt Poſt, or complimenting the priviledge you have to put poor <hi>Orantes</hi> upon the rack, that you may give him
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:99072:46"/>the pleaſure of a Cure; Ah charming <hi>Aſteria</hi> you know your Power, and 'tis no matter what I confeſs, <hi>I,</hi> am ſure you know that all my Streams of Bliſs being derived from one ſourſe, I ſubſiſt no longer than the benign <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ountain gives her ſelf; and how great, how pleaſant an one is it to find ſweet <hi>Aſteria,</hi> arguing me into into my own Happineſs, that my ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould be the effect of her Care and my Joy, the product of her Love: well, ſure it is not what <hi>I</hi> am, but what I think ſhe would have me, that makes me happy; for I never can give any account of my ſelf, but as I am ſenſible of the ſoft impreſſions of her kindneſs, or the ruffer impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of her Favour; I muſt therefore now with all the force of Love and Gratitude, own the delight you gave me, at thoſe two irreſiſtible Charms of Wit and Kindneſs, and deſcending from a perſon ſufficient to inſpire Love without them both, are enough to juſtifie the truth of my profeſſing to devote to ſweet obliging <hi>Aſteria</hi> my Love, my Life, my All; they are
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:99072:46"/>yours Madam, by the undoubted Right of a thouſand Merits, and a deathleſs Paſſion, ſecured by all thoſe Holy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations, that our Reaſon commands us to hold binding; Ah <hi>Aſteria,</hi> your dear Image is no more to be divided from my Soul, then my Soul from my Body; my Love and my Life ſhall know but one end; I am big with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of hearing this day from whence the only good news of my Life can come. I ſit telling the hours as I have a thouſand times done the miles. When I have wiſhed the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Horſe could flye; truly dear <hi>Aſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> every thing that comes from you has ſuch a reception from me, as the thirſty Sands gives to the joyful Show<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ſuch is the eſteem <hi>Orantes</hi> makes of every thing that looks but kind from <hi>Aſteria,</hi> but its no ſit compariſon, yet ſurely <hi>Aſteria</hi> that knows he loves beyond all things on Earth; knows he will at any time make himſelf the price of <hi>Aſteria</hi>'s kindneſs; let that be a valuable price, which is all I have to offer, and the rather Heaven knows
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:99072:47"/>that ſhall never want to be offer'd well, poor <hi>Orantes</hi> loves and ſuffers, and could dye before any misfortune ſhould diveſt him of that Reſpect which will live in his Soul, whilſt Breath is in his Body; 'tis as natural to ſubmit to <hi>Aſteria,</hi> as 'tis to live, and to live and love is all one; Ah Madam, How long could I entertain you, and how little reaſon is there to ſuſpect that I have any other plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Adieu, Adieu, Bleſſings ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round you.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>XXVIII.</head>
               <p>HOw doth <hi>Delia</hi> melt her Oil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Wounds, and then for fear they ſhould heal too faſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies her Corroſives, prepares <hi>Po.</hi> for the hardeſt of Fates, with ſo ſweet a Lenitive as opiates all his Grief: But alas, when I go but two Lines farther, ſhe ſays her Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are far beyond Sea, Why, what hath <hi>Po.</hi> done to deſerve this great miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; Hath he not always clothed his Love in that true genuine Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:99072:47"/>of his Soul? Has he not offered his Blood to expiate any misfortunes of hers, and would he not at this hour drain every Vein to convince her, Man never lov'd ſo madly as he does: Yes <hi>Delia,</hi> its true, I want neither Reſolution nor Courage, if your Quiet can be bought at no cheap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate: then why, if it be a Diſpute, ſhould not <hi>Pol.</hi> carry it, and keep two ſuch Loves, as ſeparation in this kind would abſolutely bring deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to, within the four Seas; Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> Where can you be within that compaſs, that you and he may not meet often and adviſe? for if he live, he will make your eaſe the care and ſcope of all his time. Yes <hi>Delia,</hi> he has vowed it when the moſt ambitious and covetous has been at reſt, and he now ſwears not to perform it, if Honour and Truth has not forſaken the Soul of Man. Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> I have a thouſand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible troubles upon me, for fear you ſhould be perſwaded to that which will undeniably prove my death. 'Tis not Affectation nor Untruth, my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:99072:48"/>
                  <hi>Delia,</hi> as I am a Chriſtian, that it ſtops my Pen and Sight, accept the Tribute I may with your aſſiſtance wipe theſe from my Eyes, but never can that Sorrow which any affliction of yours will make inſeparable from my Soul; could I be ſuppoſed to live without <hi>Delia,</hi> my Life would be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a miſerable Knowledg, or a dull ignorance worſe than death; Is not this Argument then a fit concerns my Being, and indeed both our Intereſts of weight enough to carry the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance; but as our Love lies ſo hard at ſtake, there is nothing ought to come in competition; Sure <hi>Delia</hi> did this to try her faithful Swain, one who will out-do <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> and will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate as long as ſhe is Juſt: Come we have liv'd on the cold ſide of the Mountain a long time, Blaſts and ſharp Air have blown upon us, if we be near enough to help one another, we may climb over, go round about, or like <hi>Hannibal</hi> make our way thro' with Vinegar; we may get on the Sunny ſide, and though our Tubs be
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:99072:48"/>no bigger than <hi>Diogenes</hi>'s, we may have nothing to deſire of <hi>Alexander,</hi> but that he would ſtand between us and the Sun. Well dear <hi>Delia</hi> think of this, it will be ill driving us to deſpair, when we may not be paſt hope: Adieu; I have not a worſe Enemy to my Quiet than my Fears, as <hi>Delia</hi> will manage them; She may eaſe the torment of her ever faithful Lover <hi>Polierchus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <head>XXIX.</head>
               <p>SUre nothing ſuits the genius of this Age, worſe than <hi>Orantes,</hi> for that like a rowling Sea ſends Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after Billow, and every Blaſt changes the face of the great Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; He, like the weather-beaten Shrub upon the Beach, flouriſhes ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the more for a Calm, nor wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a Storm: Dear <hi>Aſteria</hi> is the Rock his Love grows upon, there's Merit enough for the Roots to fix in; he is now at leiſure to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the foundation all alone, free to
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:99072:49"/>Thought, the Reins are now looſe, <hi>Aſteria</hi> is the ſole Object, he ſees her with his Eyes ſhut, hears her at a hundred miles diſtance, and talks to her at the ſame; Rapture and Dream are not very unlike, yet this hath the better on it, for I can think it over and over again, and am not at the mercy of a ſtarter or a noiſe to looſe the dear Delight: Charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Aſteria, Orantes</hi> is awake, not only thinks, but knows and reſolves, and from his ſtricteſt reaſoning can averr he loves, and ſhe deſerves all, and more than he can ever pay; yet with pleaſure he is endeavouring all the diſpatch poſſible to his deſign of ſeeing and ſerving her; it is his whole buſineſs. Sir <hi>William Temple</hi> makes an ingenious deſcant upon comparing the ſteady temper of the <hi>Dutch</hi> with the more acute Wit of other Nations; he ſays one cuts like a Razor, but blunted by hard op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; the other like a Hatchet, and makes the deeper impreſſion: they are, as he ſays, more dilatory,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:99072:49"/>but more ſure both in their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Diſpatch, becauſe they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways intending what they are about; apply it dear <hi>Aſteria,</hi> and doubt not the effect, 'tis not the trifling Project of ſome one advantage that animates the Spirit of <hi>Orantes,</hi> 'tis no leſs than all the whole Cargo is at ſtake, and then ask what every one doth for that, the Miſer and the Generous are then alike. Adieu, Gratitude and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour would flouriſh upon any oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of ſerving you, and would quit all pretences for this gratifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of perfecting what I have ſo often promiſed, what I have been ſo long about, and what I hope to effect; Dear <hi>Aſteria</hi> farewel; when you can with eaſe to your own Concerns, think of one whoſe enjoyments can never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to a ceſſation of misfortune, till he hath the Bleſſing to ſee you again; Forgive this trouble, and if I may beg it, to love <hi>Orantes</hi> once more. Adieu.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>My deareſt, powerful and propitious Fate,</l>
                  <l>May all thy Hours be Quiet and Sedate:</l>
                  <l>May'ſt thou be conſtant to thy Love and Friend,</l>
                  <l>And all that makes thee Happy know no end.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:99072:50"/>
               <p>THE Relation of <hi>Delia</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, have like the ſuddain Fires you mention, ſtartled me, and made me look round for Refuge; But alas, 'tis no news to poor <hi>Pol.</hi> His Reaſon to hear ſhe hath a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Offers, and what ſhe ſays, is inforced with as many Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Prudence; the tendereſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns lie at ſtake, and nothing to ſtand in the way but unfortunate <hi>Pol.</hi> How can I think, that that, which every thing cruſhes can oppoſe ſo mighty a force, Ah <hi>Delia,</hi> my Pen is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to drop out of my hand, by all that's Sacred, cold and heavy Grief has ſeized my Heart, and my Eyes will no longer perform their Duty; For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the little ſtop I make, Dear <hi>Delia,</hi> and I will on again; Is your Proſperity, Happineſs and Honour dearer to me than my Lives Blood? and yet muſt I be the only Man to oppoſe it, Ah <hi>Delia!</hi> to what ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity am I brought, that I muſt quit both my Love and my Life; 'tis true, when ever I part with one, the other will undoubtedly follow,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:99072:50"/>But may I not hope my Adorable Dear <hi>Delia</hi> will look once back, and think, whether two Souls, the neareſt being one that ever were made, can now be parted: Conſider it <hi>Delia,</hi> let your Pity be moved to your Slave; and I do here again upon my bended Knees implore your Compaſſion; Deny it not for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens ſake, unleſs you will abandon me to all that Cruelty which would make the moſt barbarous Relent. Adieu, my Life depends upon the next, remember I have no Solicitor, none to Appeal to for help, but <hi>Delia</hi> her ſelf: Well, I have only to ſay, that unalterable as Fate, is the Paſſion and Friendſhip of poor <hi>Polierchus;</hi> or may the Eternal Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for ever hate him. Adieu.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99072:51"/>
            <head>An Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>FOR want of Care in the Printing, ſome Miſtakes are made in theſe Papers, as particularly the Second and Third Letters are joyn'd together, the former of which ends at the Word <hi>Admirer,</hi> Page 9. Line 6. The reſt of the Errors the Reader may cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect thus:</p>
            <p>Page 3. Line 2. for ſeeing, read <hi>ſuing.</hi> p. 3. l. 15. r. <hi>virtue.</hi> p. 6. l. 4. r. <hi>deſect.</hi> p. 9. l. 2. r. <hi>dwells.</hi> p. 9. l. 20. r. <hi>the ſucceſs in this.</hi> p. 11. l. 16. r. <hi>deſects.</hi> p. 12. l. 9. r. <hi>laſt.</hi> p. 19. l. 18. in ſtead of, I believe I ſhall die, r. <hi>I believe it, I ſhall die.</hi> p. 21. l. 20. r. <hi>cruſhed.</hi> p. 24. l. 15. r. <hi>with.</hi> p. 32. l. 12. r. <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of my Thoughts</hi> p. 34. l. 21. r. <hi>charged.</hi> p. 40. l. 14. r. <hi>Anchorites.</hi> p. 48. l. 1. r. <hi>ſuch.</hi> p. 52. l. 2. r. <hi>ſo little inclinable.</hi> p. 53. l. 24. r. <hi>paſt.</hi> p. 54. l. 6. r. <hi>fine.</hi> p. 56. l. 22. r. <hi>may Death and Sufferings.</hi> p. 69. l pen. r. <hi>Wound.</hi> p. 72. l. pen. r. <hi>I ſhould not eſteem.</hi> p. 74. l. 10. r. <hi>little.</hi> p. 75. l. 15. r. <hi>I ſhould not dare to.</hi> p. 79. l. 2. r. <hi>for great Merit.</hi> p. 82. l. 19. r. <hi>disfavour.</hi> p. 82. l. 22. r. <hi>ah thoſe.</hi> p. 84. l. 21. r. <hi>for beyond.</hi> p. 86. l. 11. r. <hi>as it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:99072:51"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
